Princeton University Library Collection of Modern Greek Materials, 1677-1967: Finding Aid C0958
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University Library Collection of Modern Greek Materials
1677-1967
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
C0958
3 boxes
4 folders
Consists of an open collection containing miscellaneous source material related to Modern Greek studies, including letters, documents, artwork, and other unbound manuscript items.
Scope and Contents
This open collection consists of miscellaneous source material, including letters, documents, artwork, and other unbound manuscript items, pertaining to Modern Greek studies, including such subjects as diplomacy, politics, artists and writers, and Anglo-Greek relations. There are folders for Jean François Boissonade, Agalia Ionides Coronio, W. N. Glascock, Dora d'Istria, T. Karatheodorēs, Nikos Kazantzakis, Marie-Louis Marcellus, Emmanuel Miller, Constantine Mususrus, G. G. Pappadopoulos, Edouard-Jean-Pierre Perrin, Athanasios Petridēs, Abraham Salamé, En Athēnais Epistēmonikē Hetaireia, Viscount Stratford de Redclifffe, E. M. de Vogüé, Sir George Wheler, and Frank A. H. Young. Correspondents include John Boosey, Prince Roland Bonaparte, Edward Burne-Jones, Frederick William Burton, Baron Thomas Denham, Frederika Queen of the Hellenes, Charles Samuel Keene, Vice Admiral Edward Campbell Rich Owen, Edward Poynter, Jacob Spon, Compton Mackenzie, Walter Leaf, and Dante Gabriel Rossetti. Included is a letter (1865) by Emile Crespin regarding the ravages caused by the Cholera epidemic in Constantinople and Thérapia, in Turkey. Also included are letters (1867) by an unidentified French diplomat, posted in Athens, describing trips he has taken around the Mediterranean, to such places as Jerusalem, Cairo, and Constantinople. Zosimas II (1686-1746) is represented by a series of three letters in Latin and Italian (the first signed in Greek) and a Tractatus comprised of sixteen articles in Latin (1736-1737); they were written in the town of Siátista, Macedonia, under Ottoman rule and sent to the Georg Tönnemann, S.J., in Vienna.
Later additions include a French autograph manuscript (1946) by Louis Robert describing an archeological trip to Turkey and a cotton handkerchief memorializing the Cyprus Convention of 4 June 1878; an autograph album (ca. 1896-1916) of nurse Muriel Bois who worked at the Norland Institute (1906) and the Jenny Lind Infirmary (1907) in England, and who was in Greece (ca. 1914-1916), including watercolor and pencil drawings (a number by children) and contributions by Greek princesses (Olga, Elizabeth, Marina, Margarita, and Theodora); 22 letters (1929-1937) by Prince Nicholas to V. C. Scott O'Connor; and a long letter (1700, copy) by Sieur de Berquin to French administrator Michel Bégon about a diplomatic incident involving French ambassador Charles de Ferriol at the court of Mustafa II in Constantinople. Nine letters to Soutsos, Michael Vodas (1784-1864) including three letters from his father, Grēgorios, one from his brother, Nikolaos, both written in Greek and one letter from his son, Iōannēs, written in French, all of the letters dated between 1828-1839; one anonymous letter dated August 2, 1725 regarding a miraculous relic in Cyprus; 28 letters (1829-1830) addressed to Bory de Saint-Vincent, leader of the French expedition to Morea during the Greek War of Independence, from officers and other members of the expedition force, relating to the state of affairs in Morea, after a period of anarchy, and other matters of political and scientific interest; French list of imported and exported products of the island of Crete, their approximate values, and the rights to which they are subjected (1834); 11 handwritten manuscripts of esnaphia ragiadōn from Constantinople dated 1834 and signed by G. Mantzouranēs; 3 French manuscripts, ca. 1835:--one relating to the island of Samos, another on the financial state of Greece accompanied by a printed brochure (1836) prepared by George Finlay containing an essay on the principles of bank applied on the state of Greece, the third on the Greek political leaders.
Additions also include a correspondence book containing copies of 35 letters (1738-1739) by the French trader Charles Guieu, based in Smyrna, to his brothers established in Chania (2nd largest city in Crete), regarding coffee, cotton, indigo and other products sold through Smyrna and Constantinople; 3 mimeographed folio sheets of Maxwell Anderson's account of the Nazi atrocities at the Greek village of Distomo in June 1944; "Ston Hellēnoitaliko Polemon tou 1940," bound autograph manuscript diary (24 pp.) compiled by the leader of the "skapanisses" of the National Youth Organization (E.O.N.) from 29/10/1940 to 12/01/1941; autograph manuscript (4 pp.) of the Diocese of Caesarea in Cappadocia (1906) written in Karamanli dialect signed by the Metropolitan Amvrosios and others with stamps and an authentication dated 1912; notebook of an autograph manuscript report of the Major of the Police Department of Mytilēnē (Lesbos Island, Greece), Grēg. Katsarea, during the German occupation from 1941 to 1942; Max Merten case, autograph and typed manuscripts, 1957-1959; AMs (4 pp.) of the County Court of Chania (Greece), 1891 regarding a case where the defendant is Eleutherios Venizelos; AMs (30 pp.) of a plan for the reconstruction of the judicial power in Crete (Greece) signed by I. Skaltsounēs, January 3, 1880; AMs (5 pp.) of an announcement regarding legislative reforms in Crete by the governor of the island, I. Phōtiadēs dated Chania, June 12, 1879; 2 letters by the legislator of Crete, I. Skaltsounēs, regarding the criminal and political law of the island dated 1879; Compton Mackenzie's "Euboea Fifty Years Ago" [1966] manuscript; 11 signed autograph letters from Lord Dunsany (E. J. M. D. Plunkett) to violinist May Harrison, with a corrected typescript of his poem "To the Children of Greece" and a transcript by May Harrison of the account of a Yugoslav soldier; and letters from Pre-Raphaelites Edward Burne-Jones and Dante Gabriel Rossetti to members of the prominent Ionides family.
The oversize box includes 9 pencil drawings by Jules Coignet, made during a trip to Greece and Turkey in 1844, including scenes of Smyrna (Turkey), Rhodes (Greece), Beirut (Lebanon). 4 paper sheets: one Greek manuscript letter (34 x 21.3 cm.); one diploma of membership in the Athenian Society of Natural History (47.4 x 39.5 cm.); two broadsides of statutes of the Society both in Greek (42 x 31.5 cm.) and German (42 x 31.5 cm.). 4 watercolors by Roxanē Karatza depicting the genealogic trees of: the family Mavroyeni (1894); the family Antoine Rosetti (undated); the family Callimachi (undated); and the family Diamanti Draco Soutzo (c. 1894). 1 printed leaf (70.3 x 56 cm.) of the constitutional law of Greece dated 1864 and inscribed "To Neon Hellēnikon Syntagma: Eis to onoma tēs hagias kai homoousiou kai adiairetou Triados. Hē en Athēnais B' tōn Hellēnōn ethnikē syneleusis, psēphizei." Text written in six columns; printed frame. At the end of the text we read: "En Athēnais, tē 16ē Noemvriou 1864. Geōrgios A'. Ho proedros tēs Syneleuseōs, Iōannēs Mesēnezēs, Ho Proedros tēs Hieras Synodou, Theophilos - Hoi Hypourgoi K. Kanarēs, S. Sōtēropoulos, A.Ch. Lontos, Th.P. Deligiannēs, A. Koumoundouros, A. Karnalēs.
This miscellaneous collection was established in 2003 to provide a way to locate small accessions of Modern Greek-related material that the Library has acquired with support from the Program in Hellenic Studies.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Custodial History
The collection was formed as a result of a departmental practice of combining into one collection manuscript material of various accessions relating to a particular author.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired with matching funds provided by the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund.
Purchased from Roy Davids, Richard Ford, Rodolphe Chamonal, Traces-Ecrites, Librairie Michel Bouvier, Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre, Petros Vergos, AJASSE Librarie Ancienne, Robert van den Graven in 2003-2011 and gifts from Program in Hellenic Studies with matching funds provided by the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund (AM 2004-45, 2006-125, 2007-33, 2007-53, 2008-15, 2008-64, 2008-87, 2009-6, 2009-82, 2009-85, 2009-87, 2009-88, 2009-94, 2009-122, 2009-123, 2009-131, 2010-54, 2010-112, 2011-3, 2011-84, 2012-1, 2012-90, 2014-16, 2016-33, 2017-61).
Appraisal
Nothing was removed from the collection.
Archeology -- Turkey -- History -- Sources.; Art patrons -- England -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Cholera -- Turkey -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Diplomatic and consular service, British -- Turkey -- 19th century.; Diplomatic and consular service, French -- Greece -- Athens -- 19th century.; Epidemics -- Turkey -- History -- Sources.; Inscriptions, Greek.; Athens (Greece) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Beirut (Lebanon) -- 19th century -- Pictorial works.; Cairo (Egypt) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Euboea (Greece)-- Description and travel -- 20th century.; Greece -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Greece -- History -- War of Independence, 1821-1829 -- Sources.; Greece -- Politics and government -- 1832-1862.; Istanbul (Turkey) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Istanbul (Turkey) -- History -- Sources.; Izmir (Turkey) -- 19th century -- Pictorial works.; Jerusalem (Israel) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Rhodes (Greece) -- 19th century -- Pictorial works.; Smyrna (Turkey) -- Commerce -- 19th century.; Tarabya (Turkey) -- History -- Sources.; Turkey -- Description and travel -- 20th century.; Turkey -- History -- Mahmud II, 1808-1839 -- Sources.; Turkey -- History -- Mustafa II, 1695-1703 -- Sources.; Autograph albums -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Drawings -- 19th century; Societé des Sciences d'Athènes; Bégon, Michel; Boissonade, Jean-François, 1774-1857.; Coignet, Jules Louis Philippe, 1798-1860; Ferriol, Charles, marquis d'Argental, comte de, 1637-1722; Guieu, Charles; Miller, Emmanuel, 1812-1867; Nikolaos, Prince of Greece (1872-1936); Pappadopoulos, G. G. (Grēgorios G.), 1819-1873
- Anderson, Maxwell, 1944 June; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  AM 2011-113
  Scope and Contents
  3 mimeographed folio sheets of an account of the Nazi atrocities at the Greek villages of Distomo in June 1944.
- Berquin, Sieur de, 1700 May 4; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 2)
  AM 2009-94
  ALS (1700, copy) 27 pp., to French administrator Michel Begon about a diplomatic incident involving French ambassador Charles de Ferriol at the court of Mustafa II in Constantinople.
  The author may have been an artist (possibly Nicolas Berquin?) as the letter includes 2 small drawings of Turkish costume, and the second half talks about the places he visited and drew.
- Bois, Muriel, 1896-1916; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 3)
  AM 2009-82
  Autograph album (ca. 1896-1916), including watercolor and pencil drawings and contributions from several Greek princesses (Elisabeth, Margarita, Olga, Theodora).
- Boissonade, Jean Francois, undated; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 4)
  AM 2008-87
  5 ALsS by Boissonade to fellow Hellenist Jean-Francois Gail (1795-1845) about their translation work.
- Bory de Saint-Vincent, 1829-1830; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 5)
  AM 2010-112
  28 ALsS (1829-1830) addressed to Bory de Saint-Vincent, leader of the French expedition to Morea.
- Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898, Letter to Alexander ("Alecco") Ionides, 1840-1898, 1880; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 6)
  AM 2017-61
  Detailed two-page letter from artist Edward Burne-Jones to his patron and friend, the businessman and patron of the arts Alexander ("Alecco" or "Aleco") Ionides (1840-1898) regarding payments for Burne-Jones's paintings Girl in Yellow, Pan and Psyche, and Wheel of Fortune.
- Coignet, Jules Louis Philippe, 1844; Coignet, Jules Louis Philippe, 1798-1860; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  Acquired with matching funds provided by the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2009-87)
  Conists of (9) pencil drawings by Coignet, made during a trip to Greece and Turkey in 1844, including scenes of Smyrna (Turkey), Rhodes (Greece), and Beirut (Lebanon). Drawings are captioned and signed by the artist. They also bear a stamp in ink: "Vente J. Coignet".
- Connor, James, 1818-1819; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 7)
  AM 2006-66
  ALS (1819) to his brother Samuel in Dublin. The letter ("No. 2") includes excerpts from his journal, 18 November 1818 - 25 January 1819, describing his experiences on a boat traveling from Malta, to Crete, among the Greek archipelago, and ending in Constantinople.
- Coronio, Agalia Ionides, 1834-1906, 1888-1906; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 8)
  AM 2004-45
  5 ALsS to Ms. Coronio from Edward Burne-Jones, Frederick William Burton, Charles Samuel Keene, Edward Poynter, and Walter Leaf; 1 ALS by Edward Poynter to "Miss Ionides," Agalia's sister Helen Euphrosyne ["Nellie"], who later married Dr. William McNeill Whistler, brother of James McNeill Whistler.
- County Court of Chania (Greece), 1891, 1 box (Box 1, Folder 9)
  AM 2012-1
  AMs regarding a case where the defendant is Elutherios Venizelos.
- Crespin, Emile, 1865; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Lettre de 1865 sur le cholera a Constantinople.
- Cyprus Convention, 1878 June 4; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 11)
  AM 2009-6
  Commemorative handkerchief.
- Diocese of Caesarea in Cappadocia, 1906; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 11)
  AMs written in Karamanli dialect dated 1906.
- Dunsany, Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett, Baron, 1878-1957, Letters to May Harrison, 1944-1950; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 12)
  AM 2016-33
  11 signed autograph letters from Lord Dunsany (E. J. M. D. Plunkett) to violinist May Harrison, written from Dunsany Castle, Dunstrall Priory, and Cadogan Square, with a corrected typescript of his poem "To the Children of Greece" and a transcript by May Harrison of the account of a Yugoslav soldier. Harrison had asked Dunsany to write a poem highlighting the desperate condition of Greek children following German occupation, to be read at a charity concert that never took place but appeared in To Awaken Pegasus and Other Poems (1949).
- Esnaphia, 1834; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 13)
  AM 2010-115
  (11) autograph manuscripts from Constantinople dated 1834 and signed by G. Mantzouranēs.
- Essai sur les principles de Banque appliques a l'etat actuel de la Grece, 1836; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 14)
  AM 2011-3
  Printed essay by George Finlay.
- Ethniko Komitato, 1937-1973; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2013-21)
  Greek resistance organization archive. Contains material relating to Ethniko Komitato (National Revolutionary Committee of Greece), which operated under the Axis occupation of Greece and fought for the freedom of the homeland and the rights of the Greeks during the World War II. Included are autograph and typed manuscripts, such as requests; certificates regarding Nikolaos Stauropoulos' membership to the National Revolutionary Committee; reports to the Committee by N. Stauropoulos; agendas of the Committee; a list of the board members; the founding document and the National Line of the Committee; two handwritten issues (dated 15 and 18 April, 1945 respectively) of the newspaper "Ethnika Neiata" (National Youth), with crossed out title " Hē ephēmeridoula mas"; four essays by Nikolaos Stauropoulos or Atellanos: "Einai akoma kairos"; "Ho agōnas sta ergostasia"; "Ho proskopismos kai hē agōgē tōn hellēnopaidōn"; and "To noēma tēs ethnikēs antistasēs kai hoi neoi"; an identification card of Nikolaos Stauropoulos; an obituary for Nikos Kollaros; a signed letter by Giōrgos Stauropoulos to his brother Nikolaos; a signed letter to Nikolaos Stauropoulos by Vyrōn (unknown last name); miscellaneous handwritten notes; 72 black-and-white photographs dated 1937-1966; and ephemera. Included also is a pamphlet dated April 6, 1941. The National Revolutionary Committee of Greece worked closely throughout the German occupation with almost all the internal resistance organizations and helped strengthen several rebel groups.
  Guerrillas -- Greece -- 20th century.; Human rights -- Greece.; World War, 1939-1945 Underground movements Greece.; Greece -- Politics and government -- 1935-1967.; Greece -- History -- Occupation, 1941-1944.; Correspondence.; Ephemera -- 20th century; Manuscripts, Greek -- 20th century.; photographs -- 20th century.
- Frederika, Queen of the Hellenes, 1917-1981, 1965 March 29; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 17)
  AM 18545
  TLS to Robert Goheen, 1965.
- French Diplomat in Athens: Letters, 1867; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 18)
  AM 2007-53
  6 ALs (April - September 1867) describing trips around the Mediterranean, inlcuding Jerusalem, Beirut, Bethlehem, Alexandria, Cairo, Cosntantinople, Smyrna, Athens.
- Glascock, W. N. (William Nugent), 1787?-1847, 1845; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 19)
  AM 1999-30
  2 ALsS (1845) to Vice Admiral Edward Campbell Rich Owen.
- Guieu, Charles, 1738-1739; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 20)
  AM 2011-84
  Correspondence book (1738-1739) of French trader based in Smyrna (today's Izmir, Turkey).
- Istria, Dora d', comtesse, 1828-1888, 1859 November 3; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 21)
  AM 2008-64
  ALS (1859) to [Emile Littre].
- Karatheodores, T., fl 1880s, 1881; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 22)
  AM 1998-37
  TLS (1881, in Greek) to Athanasios P. Petrides; AMs (1881, in Greek) by Petrides about Etudes sur les Tchinghaines; ou, Bohemiens de l'Empire Ottoman (1870) by A. G. Paspates.
- Karatza, Roxane, circa 1894; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2009-123)
  Consists of four watercolors depicting: 1) the genealogical tree of the Mavroyeni family (1894); 2) the genealogical tree of the Antoine Rosetti family; 3) the genealogical tree of the Callimachi family; and the genealogical tree of the Diamanti Draco Soutzo family (circa 1894).
- Kazantzakis, Nikos, 1883-1957, 1849-1905; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 23)
  AM 1997-105
  6 postcards and 8 letters (1849-1965), from Nikos and Helene Kazantzakis to "Banine."
- King, Jonas, 1792-1869, 1855 October 2; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 24)
  AM 2006 Pyne-Henry
  ALS, Athens, Greece, 2 October 1855, to Michael D. Kalopothakes regarding King's missionary work in Athens.
- Mackenzie, Compton, 1882-1972, 1966; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 25)
  AM 2014-16
  "Euboea Fifty Years Ago": typed manuscript, 5 pp., with holograph corrections, signed by Mackenzie. Given at a Charity Matinee of St Martin-in-the-Fields Church, Trafalgar Square, London.
- Marcellus, Marie-Louis, 1839; 1 box (Box 1, Folder 26)
  AM 2006-125
  ALsS, 1839, 4 pp. total. Drafts of letters to be sent with copies of Souvenirs de l'Orient. Correspondents: David, Bertie Armand, [Dermousseaux] de Givre, Nettement de la Mode, Le Cte de Partoret, de Genoade.
- Maurokoukoulakēs, D., 1934-1935; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
  AM 2013-84
  24 architectural drawings on onionskin paper of churches in Crete.
- Max Merten Case, 1957-1959; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
  AMs and TMs.
- Miller, E., 1856 November 12; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  AM 2005-94
  ALS (n.d.) to "Mon cher Monsieur" regarding teh date of a Greek inscription; ALS (12 November 1856) to a collaborator of Brosset.
- Miller, Emmanuel, 1812-1886, 1845-1867; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
  AM 2009-85
  18 ALsS to various correspondents, 1845-1867.
- "Miraculous relic in Cyprus", 1725 August 2; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Anonymous letter, 2 August 1725.
- Musurus, Constantine, 1807-1891, 1886 February 3; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
  ALS (1886) to Baron Thomas Denman.
- Notebook, 1941-1942; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
  AMs of a report of the Major of the Police Department of Mytilene (Lesbos Island, Greece), Greg. Katserea, during the German occupation from 1941 to 1942.
- Notes, 1835; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Report on the Greek political leaders in 1835.
- Pappadopoulos, G. G. (1819-1874), 1845; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
  AM 2013-57
  Autograph draft letter, dated 28 August 1845, by Pappadopoulos on the "improvement of the church music through the Vienna reform," addressed to the prime-minister of Greece [Kolettes, Ioannes].
- Patmore, Derek, 1967; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Typed manuscript of "The Story of my Literary Review 'Greek Horizons'" and a holograph (1967).
- Perrin, Edouard-Jean-Pierre, 1852-1926, 1872; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
  AM 2007-33
  6 ALsS (May - October, 1872) by Perrin to his parents, while he was a student in the l'Ecole Navale he sails in the Aegean, visiting such places a sAthens and Smyrna.
- Les persecutions antihelleniques en Bulgarie et dans les pays provisoirement occupes par les Bulgares, 1917; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
  AM 2014-65
- Phildelpheus, Alexandros, 1899; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
  AM 2009-122
  Autograph Greek manuscript (1899), 11 pp. Lecture or study on the visit of "The Apostle Paul in Areios Pagos."
- Phōtiadēs, I., 1879 June 12; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
  AMs of an announcement regarding legislative reforms in Crete dated Chania, June 12, 1879.
- Programma Agrot. Oik. Oikonomias, 1ēs Epith/seōs Geōrgias, 1960-1966; 1 box
  - Programma Agrot. Oik. Oikonomias, 1ēs Epith/seōs Geōrgias, 1960, 1 box (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Programma Agrot. Oik. Oikonomias, 1ēs Epith/seōs Geōrgias, 1960, 1966; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Robert, Louis, 1946; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 3)
  AM 2008-15
  Manuscript d'un voyage archeologique en Turquie, 1946.
- Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882, Letters to the Ionides Family, 1866-1879; 1 box
  Consists of letters from Dante Gabriel Rossetti to various members of the Ionides family, a prominent family of Greek descent in London in the 19th century known for their patronage of the arts.
  - Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882, Letters to Euphrosyne Cassavetti (Ionides), 1822-1896, 1870 June 20; 1879 January 1-February 9; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Three letters from Rossetti at 16 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, to Euphrosyne Cassavetti (1822-1896), the daughter of Constantine Ionides (1775-1852) and a patron of the arts. An 1870 letter discusses dresses Cassavetti was obtaining for Rossetti, presumably for the use of a model. The two 1879 letters relate to Cassavetti's purchase of one of Rossetti's 1869 drawings of her daughter, Maria Cassavetti Zambaco (1843-1914).
  - Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882, Letter to Alexander ("Alecco") Ionides, 1840-1898, 1866 February 13; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 5)
    One-page letter from Rossetti at 16 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, to Alexander ("Alecco" or "Aleco") Ionides (1840-1898), rearranging a meeting with Ionides, citing the need to dedicate all of his time to painting.
  - Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882, Letter to Maria Cassavetti Zambaco, 1843-1914, circa 1870; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Three-page letter from Rossetti at 16 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, to Maria Cassavetti Zambaco (1843-1914), a painter, sculptor, and favored art model for the Pre-Raphaelites, including Rossetti and Edward Burne-Jones. In this undated letter, Rossetti writes to Zambaco as a fellow artist, thanking her for allowing him to use her art model.
- Salame, Abraham, fl. 1816, 1821-1828; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 7)
  ALS (1828) to John Boosey; 4 ALsS (1821, n.d.) to unidentified persons.
- Samos [L'ile grecque de Samos deviant principaute turque], 1835; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 8)
  AMs.
- Skaltsounes, I., 1879-1880; 1 box
  - Skaltsounes, I., 1880; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 9)
    AMs of a plan for the reconstruction of the judicial power in Crete, 1880.